Guide to the Pacific University Early Manuscript Serials 1857-1875
Pacific University Archives
Pacific University Student Early Manuscript Serials
1857-1875
MS.71
Pacific University, Archives http://www.pacificu.edu/library/services/archives/ 2043 College Way Forest Grove, OR, 97116 503-352-1405 archives@pacificu.edu
1.0 cubic foot 2 boxes
The students at Pacific University and Tualatin Academy, which was one of the earliest institutions of higher education in Oregon, created many literary magazines in the 1850s and 1860s. This collection contains many examples of such handwritten serial publications authored and edited by these students.
Collection is open for research.
No accruals are expected.
Historical Note
The students at Pacific University and Tualatin Academy, which was one of the earliest institutions of higher education in Oregon, created many literary magazines in the 1850s and 1860s.
This collection contains handwritten serial publications created by the students of Pacific University and Tualatin Academy. It is not clear how (or how much) they circulated. They look like a printed format of a publication. Most of the articles have to do with do with morals and values, such as happiness and temperance, as well as subjects of general interest to the student writers. Some examples of these interests include astrology, arts, education, and current events. A few of the editorials touch on student life at Pacific University and Tualatin Academy, but are very spare in detail.
Eells, Edwin; Hinman, Arvid; Lyman, William; Walker, Charles H.
Pacific University; Student activities; Students--Oregon; Tualatin Academy; Universities and colleges--Oregon--Periodicals
Student Life
- The Academic Star, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  5 volumes and selected articles. 1857-58. Editors: C.H. Walker, Edwin Eells, Theodore Silver, T.B. Hendery.
- The American Star, 1857-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  4 volumes from 1857-1859. Editors: Ch. H. Walker, Edwin Eells, Theodore Silver, T.H. Handley.
- The College Echo, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  7 volumes. 1859-1860. Editors: J.E. Walker, Thomas B. Hoover, E. Eells, Myron Eells, C.S. Dustin, C.H. Raffety. "The College Echo is a semi-monthly journal published by a division of the students of the Pacific University and is devoted to Education, Temperance, Agriculture, Art, + Science and General Intelligence."
- The Golden Wreath, Circa 1865-1870 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  1 volume. Editors: William D. Lyman, Sarah Lyman, Arvid Hinman, Levi Walker, Rebecca Buxton, Amanda Tottle. General writings on topics of interest to the editors.
- The Literary Star, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  1 volume. 1875. Editors: Mefers, Lyman, Collier, Atkinson. Members of the Gamma Sigma Society. Purpose: “Give members of the Gamma Sigma Society an opportunity to make public their thoughts on various subjects of interest.” Short essays by members.
- The New Comet, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  1 volume. Editor: J.W. Johnson. "Devoted to moral, physical, and intellectual improvement." Short essays on different topics.
- The Rosebud, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  3 volumes. 1857-58 no. 1-3. Editors: A.A. Grub, M.I. Scott, D. Hill, A.E. Stoll, T.L. Jolly.
- The Star of the West, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  4 volumes. 1858. Vol. 1: no. 1, 3, 5, and a special issue entitled “The Starry Gems,” containing selections from the compositions of each of the contributors to the “Star of the West” during the previous term. Publishing committee: Edwin Eells, Charles H. Walker, J.B. Hardly. Essays written by: Thomas B. Hoover, W.W. Black, Mary E. Morris, Myron Eells, Albert Finney, Mary A. Reasoner, Marcus W. Walker, Woodson Scoggins, Edwin Eells, L.M. Tanner, Leremiah Walker, David Stewart, Tom Thumb, P.S. Jolly, C.B. Green, M.E. Story, T.B. Hardley, Cyrus H. Walker, S.W. Hall.
- The Students' Journal, 1859-1861 (Box 2, Folders 9-11)
  16 issues. 1859-61. “Semimonthly Paper…It is devoted to temperance, arts, science and general intelligence.” Editors: James Purdin, M.H. Cotter, F.N. Reasoner. Richard L. Lewis, H.W. Scott, J.W. Jolly, J.E. Walker, Myron Eells, T. Huddlestun, D. Stewart, Kate Owens.
- The Students Magazine, 1859-1859 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  4 issues. "Devoted to Science, Agriculture, Arts, Improvement, Historical Researchers, and General Intelligence." Editors: J.W. Jolly, E. Eells, C.W. Raffety.
- The Vernal Wreath, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  4 volumes. 1861. Editor: C.H. Raffety, J.W. Jolly, F.N. Reasoner. Authors: Nancy T. Marty, H. Naylor, L. Hines, J. Naylor, E. Reasoner, Mary Harell, R.L. Boyles, Edwin Eells, Cicero Hines, John R. Walker and others. “A semimonthly sheet published by a division of the students of the Pacific University. Devoted to science, literature, finance and general intelligence.”
- The Wreath, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  1 volume, May 25, 1860. Editor: Susan L. Tanner. 1 volume. 1860. Authors: Charles H. Raffety, W. Brown. "…a semi-monthly journal published by a division of the students of Pacific University, and is devoted to science, literature, and general intelligence."
- The Young Men's Journal, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  1 volume. Editor: R.B. Willmott. Published by the students of Forest Grove (Pacific) University.
- The Young Oregonian, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  1 volume. 1859. "Printed by the students of Tualatin Academy." Editor: Wesley Black.